<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter id="overview">
	<title>Overview</title>
	<para>
	Scribble is a simple text based language for describing interactions between multiple
	parties. 
	</para>
	  
	<para><emphasis>
	"Scribbling is necessary for architects, either physical or computing, since all
	great ideas of architectural construction come from that unconscious
	moment, when you do not realise what it is, when there is no concrete
	shape, only a whisper which is not a whisper, an image which is not an
	image, somehow it starts to urge you in your mind, in so small a voice but
	how persistent it is, at that point you start scribbling"</emphasis> - Kohei Honda 2007
	</para>

	<para>
	Scribble is a family of notations designed to describe interactions at different levels
	of abstract. The first level, described in this guide, is known as the <emphasis>Protocol</emphasis>
	notation. This notation is intended to provide an abstract description of the communication
	behaviour. Subsequent levels of notation add constraints and state definitions ultimately
	reaching the level of description more traditionally associated with programming languages.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	In the world of programming languages, the measure of the simplicity of a language
	is based on its representation of a simple 'hello world' example. The Scribble
	Protocol representation of such an example would be: 
	</para>
	
	<informalexample>
  		<programlisting>
			<emphasis role="bold">protocol</emphasis> HelloWorld {
			    <emphasis role="bold">participant</emphasis> You, World;
			    Hello <emphasis role="bold">from</emphasis> You <emphasis role="bold">to</emphasis> World;
			}
  		</programlisting>
  	</informalexample>

	<para>
	The notation will be explained in more detail in this guide, but basically the
	protocol is named 'HelloWorld', and describes the communication behaviour between
	two participants (or parties). A single interaction has been defined, sending a message
	of type 'Hello' from participant 'You' to participant 'World'.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	In the following chapter we will explore the main constructs of the protocol
	notation. Then we will explore a range of examples, before concluding with a
	brief overview of some more advanced constructs that are still under development.
	</para>
	
</chapter>
