<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter id="architecture">
	<title>Architecture</title>
	<para>
	</para>
	
	<section>
		<title>OSGi Infrastructure</title>
		
		<para>
		The Scribble architecture is based on OSGi, to provide a means
		of managing the individual modules, but without causing tight
		coupling.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		Service bundles enable implementations to be specified that
		implement defined interfaces. Other services can then
		request access to services that implement a particular interface.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		The OSGi service container takes responsibility of managing the
		services, and providing access to requesting components.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		This provides flexibility for Scribble tooling in two respects:
		</para>
		
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
			Replaceable
			<para>
			The implementation of a particular Scribble interface can
			easily be replaced. This enables different research or
			industry groups to replace specific modules, with
			alternative implementations, while still reusing other
			modules.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			Extensibility
			<para>
			Some aspects of the architecture allow for multiple implementations
			of the same interface. Therefore, using OSGi, enables
			additional implementations of the same interface to be
			easily plugged in, without having to define any
			additional configuration information.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</section>
		
	<section>
		<title>Core Components</title>

		<section>
			<title>Protocol Notation</title>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Protocol Parser</title>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Protocol Model</title>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Error Logging</title>
			
			<para>
			There is a generic logging API within the Scribble
			framework that can be used for reporting errors,
			warnings, information or debuging details.
			This API is <emphasis>org.scribble.core.logging.ScribbleLogger</emphasis>.
			</para>
			
			<para>
			The methods generally take two parameters, a message
			and a property map. The message is simply a description
			of the issue being reported. The property map contain
			specific details about the issue being reported.
			</para>
			
			<para>
			For example, when the parser detects a problem, it
			can report the nature of the problem, and provide the
			location of the issue in the source file.
			</para>
			
			<section>
				<title>Internationalization</title>
				
				<para>
				To enable errors reported from the Scribble parser
				and validation modules, in a number of different
				languages, internationalization should be used.
				</para>
			
				<para>
				The following code fragment provides an example
				of how internationalization can be achieved, using
				parameterised messages.
				</para>	
				
				<programlisting>
logger.error(org.scribble.core.util.MessageUtil.format(
				java.util.PropertyResourceBundle.getBundle(
						"org.scribble.core.validation.rules.Messages"),
										"_EXISTING_DECLARATION",
										new String[]{elem.getName()}),
										obj.getProperties());
				</programlisting>
				
				<para>
				The main message content is obtained from a
				properties file, with the name being supplied
				as the first parameter to the <emphasis>getBundle</emphasis>
				method. The property file must be placed
				the correct package within the
				<filename>src/main/resources</filename> folder, to
				ensure the properties are correctly packaged
				by maven.
				</para>
				
				<para>
				The messages within the property files can have
				values that include parameters. Parameters are
				numbered in sequential order, and defined between
				curly braces (e.g. {n} where 'n' is the number).
				For example,
				</para>
				
				<programlisting>
_EXISTING_DECLARATION=Declaration already exists for name '{0}'				
				</programlisting>
				
				<para>
				This message only has a single parameters.
				</para>
				
				<para>
				In the previous code fragment, the
				<emphasis>MessageUtil.format()</emphasis>
				method takes the message as the first parameter,
				and an array of strings as the parameter values
				to be substituted in the message. So in the
				code fragment, the value in the <emphasis>elem.getName()</emphasis>
				would be substituted in the <emphasis>{0}</emphasis>
				parameter of the <emphasis>_EXISTING_DECLARATION</emphasis>
				message, and then reported to the Scribble logger.
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Type Resolution</title>
			
			<note>
			<para>
			Placeholder for component to resolve references from one
			model to other models and types. This will be required
			where one protocol references an external protocol - to
			enable other validation to span across the multiple
			protocols seemlessly.
			</para>
			</note>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Validation Manager and Validators</title>
			
			<para>
			The validation manager, when used in a OSGi runtime
			environment, will listen for the activation of any
			implementations of the
			<filename>org.scribble.core.validation.Validator</filename>
			interface.
			</para>
			
			<para>
			This means that the validation of any model can be
			performed using the 
			<emphasis>org.scribble.core.validation.ValidationManager</emphasis>,
			rather than having to obtain instances of
			multiple implementations of the <filename>Validator</filename>
			interface.
			</para>
			
			<para>
			When the <filename>ValidatorManager</filename> is used
			outside of an OSGi environment, it is necessary for the
			validators to be added to the manager by other means.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Command Line Actions</title>
		
		<para>
		The first step is to define the command implementation
		of the <emphasis>org.scribble.command.Command</emphasis>
		interface. This can be created in the
		<emphasis>org.scribble.command</emphasis> Eclipse plugin.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		To the initialise the command, as part of an OSGi
		runtime environment, the command implementation can be
		instantiated in the <emphasis>org.scribble.command</emphasis>
		plugin's <emphasis>Activator</emphasis>, and then
		registered with the bundle context.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		If the command requires other OSGi services, then
		these can be established by setting up service listeners
		for the relevant service interface classes. When
		OSGi services are registered, then the relationship
		can be established.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		This command mechanism will generally only be used
		as part of the command line approach, and therefore
		does not need to be initialised in other ways. However
		other dependency injection techniques could be
		used if appropriate.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		The only remaining step is to create the scripts
		necessary to enable a user to invoke the command.
		This can be achieved by copying one of the existing
		scripts, in the <filename>distribution/src/main/release</filename>
		folder (such as <filename>parse.sh</filename>),
		and modify the parameter details as necessary.
		</para>
		
		<note>
		<para>
		The first parameter of the Java application, invoked
		within the script, must be the name of the command.
		This must match the value returned by the
		<emphasis>getName()</emphasis> method on the command
		interface.
		</para>
		</note>
	</section>
</chapter>
